Peyton Rous Papers 1909-1970 Mss.B.R77
American Philosophical Society
Peyton Rous Papers
Circa 1917-1970
Mss.B.R77
American Philosophical Society
61.0 Linear feet
For his pioneering research on the link between viruses and cancer, the pathologist Francis Peyton Rous was awarded the Nobel Prize in Medicine in 1966. Working primarily at the Rockefeller Institute after 1909, Rous first came to notice for his theoretical construction of the first blood bank for use in France during World War I, a plan ultimately implemented by his assistant, Oswald H. Robertson. Subsequently, he left an important imprint on the development of experimental medicine, partly through his own research on the origins of cancer and his administrative activities at the Rockefeller, but also as editor of the Journal of Experimental Medicine from 1921-1970. The Rous Papers include correspondence, lectures, articles, reports, laboratory records, reprints, and photographs that document all aspects of the life and work of Peyton Rous. Reflecting his work at the Institute are letters of colleagues, information on assistants, and reports to the directors (1909-1959). Additional material relates to Rous' diverse organizational interests, including the American Cancer Society, Century Association, Jane Coffin Childs Memorial Fund for Medical Research (at Yale University), Federation of American Societies for Experimental Biology, Johns Hopkins University, National Academy of Sciences, National Research Council, New York Academy of Medicine, Royal Society of Medicine Foundation, and Sloan-Kettering Institute for Cancer Research.
Rous, Peyton, 1879-1970
Bibliography
Renato Dulbecco, "Francis Peyton Rous, October 5, 1879 - February 16, 1970," Biographical Memoirs of the National Academy of Sciences 48 (1976). Call no.: 506.73 N18b v.48.
"A notable career in finding out: Peyton Rous, 1879-1970," Rockefeller University Occasional Paper 16 (1971). Call no.: B R77r.
Physiology, Biochemistry, and Biophysics Note
The papers of Peyton Rous include correspondence, lectures, articles, reports, laboratory records, reprints, and photographs. These materials record in detail Rous' long scientific career and his discoveries which revolutionized several areas in the life sciences. His discovery in 1910 that viruses cause malignant tumors in fowl and his subsequent work in tumor virology linked intellectual and disciplinary trends in medical physiology and bacteriology at the turn of the century with those of molecular biology in the 1950s. The founding of the sub-specialty of tumor virology also reoriented the course of cancer research. His innovative laboratory techniques, especially in tissue culture, advanced the course of cytology and microbiology. The files on Rous (approximately 200 folders, 1910s-1960s) contain annual reports, lectures, and papers describing these diverse studies.
During World War I, in collaboration with several colleagues at the Rockefeller Institute (notably Oswald H. Robertson), Rous devised methods for preserving human blood through the use of blood banks that made more transfusions possible. This important project is documented in the Oswald H. Robertson correspondence (1917-1960).
In addition to documenting his paradigmatic researches, the collection also contains hundreds of files on the Journal of Experimental Medicine (JEM), of which Rous was an editor from 1921 to 1970. These files contain a wealth of information on editorial policies, referee accounts, scientific controversies, and changing trends in the life sciences. Rous' broader institutional and social influence is reflected in the files on scientific institutions and organizations, including the Rockefeller Institute, the Federation of American Societies for Experimental Biology, the National Academy of Sciences, the National Research Council, and the New York Academy of Medicine.
The Rous Papers also contain material on Rous' Nobel Prize, which he received fifty-six years after his historic discovery, an interesting episode in the history of the life sciences. Rous' correspondence with several colleagues (especially with C. H. Andrewes), together with the boxes on the Nobel Prize, reveal aspects of the delayed recognition of his contributions, the controversies surrounding the question of whether tumors arose spontaneously or were induced, and the events leading to the final acceptance of his work.
The Rous correspondence is divided into two main sections: 1) personal-professional correspondence, and 2) editorial correspondence (JEM).
Series I. Correspondence:
Abbott, A. C. (Alexander Crever), 1860-1935 ( Interactions between Rous' laboratory and the University of Pennsylvania School of Hygiene and Public Health.) Correspondence (7 items) 1925 English
Alsberg, Carl, 1877-1940 ( On aspects of bacteriology in the United States Department of Agriculture Bureau of Chemistry.) Correspondence (5 items) 1920 English
Altenburg, Edgar, 1888-1967 ( On problems of the virus theory of cancer.) Correspondence (3 items) 1946 English
American Cancer Society ( Demonstrates Rous' pioneering role in basic cancer research and his continuous leadership in the field.) Correspondence (2 folders) 1945-1963 English
Andrewes, C. H. (Christopher Howard), Sir ( Detailed correspondence on tumor virology. Discussion of the delayed recognition of Rous' contributions to the study of tumors. Includes "Evidence for the Presence of Virus in a Non-Filterable Tar Sarcoma of the Fowl" and "Latent Virus Infectious and Their Possible Relevance to the Cancer Problem.") Correspondence (5 folders) 1929-1968 English
Angus, C. Franklin ( On political conditions in Europe.) Correspondence (12 items) 1935-1940 English
Barcroft, Joseph, Sir, 1872-1947 Correspondence (5 items) 1932 English
Blankenhorn, Marion Arthur, 1885-1957 ( Administrative correspondence.) Correspondence (3 folders) 1923-1953 English
Cannon, Walter B. (Walter Bradford), 1871-1945 ( Important exchanges on scientific and social aspects of research; Cannon's influence on the institutional aspects of the life sciences.) Correspondence (23 items) 1926-1939 English
Cattell, James McKeen, 1860-1944 ( On Science Service.) Correspondence (3 folders) 1920-1945 English
Childs Memorial Fund ( Demonstrates Rous' pioneering role in basic cancer research and his continuous leadership in the field. Includes correspondence, reports, and minutes.) Records (20 folders) 1937-1963 English
Cohn, Alfred E. (Alfred Einstein), 1879-1957 ( On the Rockefeller Institute.) Correspondence (5 folders) 1924-1960 English
Corner, George Washington, 1889-1981 Correspondence (3 folders) 1935-1967 English
Dean, Henry R. ( Including information on pathology in England.) Correspondence (10 folders) 1925-1960 English
Euthanasia Society of America ( Contains information on the history of cancer research.) Correspondence (4 items) 1950, n.d. English
Federation of American Societies for Experimental Biology ( Reflects Rous' institutional and social influence.) Correspondence (10 folders) 1916-1918, 1932-1954 English
Flexner, Simon, 1863-1946 ( Important administrative and scientific correspondence, especially on disciplinary trends, and women in science.) Correspondence (16 folders) [1903], 1921-1952 English
Gasser, Herbert S. (Herbert Spencer), 1888-1963 ( Institutional aspects, impressions on John H. Northrop's research.) Correspondence (7 folders) 1935-1953 English
Gratia, Andre, 1893-1950 Correspondence (2 items) 1938-1939 English
Gregg, Alan, 1890-1957 ( On biomedical research, the Rockefeller Foundation, and social aspects of biomedical sciences (including anti-Semitism).) Correspondence (4 folders) 1929-1954 English
Hanson, Frank Blair ( On the Rockefeller Foundation and physico-chemical biology.) Correspondence (14 items) 1934-1937 English
Hevesy, Georg von, 1885-1966 ( See also folder filed under " DeHevesy, George.") Correspondence (5 folders) 1959-1968 English
Jackson Memorial Laboratory ( Demonstrates Rous' pioneering role in basic cancer research and his continuous leadership in the field.) Correspondence (5 folders) 1940-1952 English
Landsteiner, Karl, 1868-1943 Correspondence (6 folders) 1920-1945 English
Levene, P. A. (Phoebus Aaron), 1869-1940 Correspondence (6 items) 1929-1938 English
National Academy of Sciences ( Reflects Rous' institutional and social influence.) Correspondence (10 folders) 1939-1947 English
National Research Council ( Reflects Rous' institutional and social influence.) Records (20 folders) 1918-1951 English
New York Academy of Medicine ( Reflects Rous' institutional and social influence.) Correspondence (9 folders) 1929-1969 English
Northrop, John Howard, 1891-1987 ( Correspondence on a wide range of scientific and institutional matters.) Correspondence (3 folders) 1929-1967 English
Rockefeller Institute ( Reflects Rous' institutional and social influence. Includes correspondence, Board of Scientific Directors, Business Manager, and Reports for Boards of Directors.) Records (4 folders) 1932-1965 English
Rous, Peyton, 1879-1970. Nobel Prize ( Reveals aspects of the delayed recognition of Rous' contributions to the study of tumors, the controversies surrounding the question of whether tumors arose spontaneously or were induced, and the events leading to the final acceptance of his work, ultimately leading to the Nobel Prize. Includes congratulatory letters, Rous' acceptance speech, newsclippings, and printed items.) Records (31 folders) 1966-1969 English
Shope, Richard E., 1901-1966 Correspondence (13 folders) 1932-1968 English
Sloan-Kettering Institute for Cancer ( Demonstrates Rous' pioneering role in basic cancer research and his continuous leadership in the field. Includes correspondence and research materials.) Correspondence (22 folders) 1955-1969 English
Stanley, Wendell M. (Wendell Meredith), 1904-1971 ( Includes problems in virus research and its connection to cancer studies.) Correspondence (2 folders) 1939-1967 English
Van Slyke, Donald D. (Donald Dexter), 1883-1971 ( Scientific correspondence and editorial correspondence related to the Journal of Experimental Medicine (JEM).) Correspondence (2 folders (17 items)) 1924-1963 English
Wyckoff, Ralph W. G. (Ralph Walter Graystone), 1897-1995 ( On Wyckoff and the growth of biophysics.) Correspondence (2 folders) 1937-1969 English
Zinsser, Hans, 1878-1940 Correspondence (3 folders) 1921-1940 English
Series II. Oswald H. Robertson Material
Robertson, Oswald Hope, 1886-1966 ( Professional and personal correspondence between Peyton Rous and his friend and colleague, Oswald H. Robertson. Included in the series is some valuable correspondence regarding the use of preserved blood and blood banks during the First World War, and discussions of later research by Robertson and Rous at the Rockefeller Institute. Also, there is a group of the scientific papers of Dr. Robertson.) Correspondence (0.5 linear feet) 1917-1960 English
Series III. Card files and Miscellaneous
Journal of Experimental Medicine (JEM) ( Contains a wealth of information on editorial policies, referee accounts, scientific controversies, and changing trends in the life sciences.) Records (25 linear feet) 1918-1948 English
Avery, Oswald Theodore, 1877-1955 ( Editorial correspondence related to the Journal of Experimental Medicine (JEM).) Correspondence (11 items) 1928-1944 English
Burnet, F. M. (Frank Macfarlane), Sir, 1899-1985 ( Editorial correspondence related to the Journal of Experimental Medicine (JEM).) Correspondence (14 items) 1935-1940 English
Chargaff, Erwin, 1905-2002 ( Editorial correspondence related to the Journal of Experimental Medicine (JEM).) Correspondence (2 items) 1937 English
Cohen, Seymour S. (Seymour Stanley), 1917- ( Editorial correspondence related to the Journal of Experimental Medicine (JEM).) Correspondence (6 items) 1945-1947 English
Dubos, Rene J. (Rene Jules), 1901-1982 ( Editorial correspondence related to the Journal of Experimental Medicine (JEM).) Correspondence (12 items) 1939-1947 English
Flexner, Simon, 1863-1946 ( Editorial correspondence related to the Journal of Experimental Medicine (JEM).) Correspondence (2 folders) 1922-1940 English
Haurowitz, Felix, 1896-1987 ( Editorial correspondence related to the Journal of Experimental Medicine (JEM).) Correspondence (9 items) 1940-1941 English
Heidelberger, Michael ( Editorial correspondence related to the Journal of Experimental Medicine (JEM).) Correspondence (3 folders) 1929-1948 English
Horsfall, Frank Lappin, 1906-1971 ( Editorial correspondence related to the Journal of Experimental Medicine (JEM).) Correspondence (28 items) 1934-1947 English
Kabat, Elvin A. (Elvin Abraham), 1914-2000 ( Editorial correspondence related to the Journal of Experimental Medicine (JEM).) Correspondence (2 folders) 1938-1948 English
Lancefield, Rebecca Craighill, 1895-1981 ( Editorial correspondence related to the Journal of Experimental Medicine (JEM).) Correspondence (9 items) 1937-1946 English
Landsteiner, Karl, 1868-1943 ( Editorial correspondence related to the Journal of Experimental Medicine (JEM).) Correspondence (14 items) 1925-1942 English
Loeb, Jacques, 1859-1924 ( Editorial correspondence related to the Journal of Experimental Medicine (JEM).) Correspondence (1 item) 1923 English
Olitsky, Peter K., 1866-1964 ( Editorial correspondence related to the Journal of Experimental Medicine (JEM).) Correspondence (24 items) 1928-1939 English
Pauling, Linus, 1901-1994 ( Editorial correspondence related to the Journal of Experimental Medicine (JEM).) Correspondence (4 items) 1942 English
Rivers, Thomas M. (Thomas Milton), 1888-1962 ( Editorial correspondence related to the Journal of Experimental Medicine (JEM).) Correspondence (23 items) 1925-1940 English
Robertson, Oswald Hope, 1886-1966 ( Editorial correspondence related to the Journal of Experimental Medicine (JEM).) Correspondence (34 items) 1930-1946 English
Rous, Peyton, 1879-1970 ( Editorial correspondence related to the Journal of Experimental Medicine (JEM).) Correspondence (6 folders) 1922-1945 English
Sabin, Albert B. (Albert Bruce), 1906-1993 ( Editorial correspondence related to the Journal of Experimental Medicine (JEM).) Correspondence (3 folders) 1930-1947 English
Salk, Jonas, 1914-1995 ( Editorial correspondence related to the Journal of Experimental Medicine (JEM).) Correspondence (10 items) 1940, 1947 English
Seibert, Florence Barbara, 1897-1991 ( Editorial correspondence related to the Journal of Experimental Medicine (JEM).) Correspondence (5 items) 1938-1940 English
Wright, George G. ( Editorial correspondence related to the Journal of Experimental Medicine (JEM).) Correspondence (13 items) 1943-1946 English
Wyckoff, Ralph W. G. (Ralph Walter Graystone), 1897-1995 ( Editorial correspondence related to the Journal of Experimental Medicine (JEM).) Correspondence (17 items) 1931-1935 English
Zinsser, Hans, 1878-1940 ( Editorial correspondence related to the Journal of Experimental Medicine (JEM).) Correspondence (2 folders) 1924-1938 English
Additional Biographical Notes:
William Meredith Stanley joined the Rockefeller Institute in 1931. After working briefly with W. J. V. Osterhout, he was transferred to the Princeton branch to set up a research project on the tobacco mosaic virus, work that focused mainly on protein chemistry. At that time virology had already grown into a major field of biomedical research, but no one had yet succeeded in isolating a single virus. Stanley's skills in bio-organic chemistry, augmented by John Howard Northrop's cooperation, resulted in 1935 in the crystallization of the tobacco mosaic virus, a technical feat that attracted international attention. Stanley's conclusion that the reproductive material in the virus was an autocatalytic protein seemed to have solved the virus mystery, and to confirm the widespread belief in the primacy of proteins in heredity. Stanley's work, for which he had received the 1946 Nobel Prize (shared with James B. Sumner and Northrop), has generally been viewed as a cornerstone of molecular biology and a major landmark in the history of medicine.
Related Archival Materials note
The papers of Rous' former assistants, Oswald Hope Robertson (call no. B R546) and James B. Murphy (B M956), contain correspondence with Rous and information on their work in establishing blood banks during the First World War and after. Rous appears as a correspondent in several other collections, including the papers of Simon Flexner, Eugene Opie, Leon Cole, and Harold Amoss.
Separated Materials note
Two sets of Rous's reprints were transferred to the Printed Materials Department for storage. These includes two boxes of reprints by Rous (call no. 616 pam.r) and seven boxes of reprints by other researchers (616 pam.ro).
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift of Francis Peyton Rous, 1969; the Rous estate, 1970; and Paul F. Cranefield, 1973 (accession numbers 1969-756ms, 1970-1563ms, and 1973-2538ms).
Arrangement note
Series I. Correspondence ca.1917-1970 47 linear feet
Series II. Oswald H. Robertson Material 1917-1960 0.5 linear feet
Series III. Card files and miscellaneous 1909-1950s 12 linear feet
Scope and Contents note
The papers of Peyton Rous are a large and diverse assemble of correspondence, manuscripts, and photographs relating to the medical researcher and Nobel laureate who developed the viral theory of the origins of cancer.
The collection includes a substantial series of files relating to Rous' involvement as editor of the Journal of Experimental Medicine, providing a glimpse into his editorial philosophy, and more generally, his philosophy on medical research.
Biographical/Historical note
A pathologist, Francis Peyton Rous, was co-recipient of the Nobel Prize in Physiology and Medicine in 1966 for his discovery of carcinogenic viruses. Born in Texas in 1879 and raised in Baltimore, Rous received his professional indoctrination entirely at Johns Hopkins, where he received both his bachelors (1900) and medical degrees (1905). After beginning his internship -- again at Hopkins -- he was quickly confirmed in his preference for research over clinical work, and therefore decided to accept a lower-paying position at the University of Michigan, rather than continue down the clinical path. Relegated to a position that had him working essentially as a technician, Rous found compensation in Ann Arbor through his department head, Alfred Warthin, who encouraged him to apply for and accept a fellowship in 1907 to study morbid anatomy at Dresden, where he honed his skills as a researcher.
Rous returned from Europe to take up a grant from the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research to pursue research on lymphocytes, during the course of which, he caught the eye of Simon Flexner, and earned a call to the staff at Rockefeller. From the time of his move to New York, Rous' research gained enormous momentum. In 1909, his most important series of experiments examined the transmission of spontaneous cancerous tumors in chickens. Preparing a cell-free filtrate from a malignant sarcoma isolated from a chicken leg and injecting it into healthy hens, Rous discovered that the recipients developed precisely the same tumors as the donors, and that the tumors could be transmitted either by direct injection or through injection into fertilized eggs, hypothesizing that a virus was the agent responsible for transmission. Other tumors, too, turned out to be similarly transmissible, with similar fidelity in producing cancers of the donors in the recipients.
Using mice, however, Rous' initial efforts to assess whether tumors could be transmitted in mammals were unavailing until in 1932, his friend and Rockefeller colleague, Richard Shope, asked Rous to investigate the benign papillomas commonly found in wild rabbits which were shown to be transmissible by cell-free extracts. Despite mounting evidence for Rous' viral theory of cancer, there was considerable resistance among medical researchers to its acceptance, who argued that Rous had discovered a condition peculiar to birds and benign tumors, rather than malignant cancers. It was not until the 1950s that subsequent research in virology changed the situation and led to its inculcation as a central element in the theory of cancer origins.
Several other projects in which Rous participated resulted in important medical advances. During the First World War, he and Oswald Robertson were instrumental in developing a citrate-dextrose solution that, when added to preserved blood, provided nourishment and prevented clotting, extending its shelf life for up to four weeks. The practical result was the establishment of the first blood banks in 1918. Rous also exerted an influence over medical research through his position as long-time co-editor of the Journal of Experimental Medicine and from the administrative heights of his perch at the Rockefeller.
Rous retired from the Institute at age 65 and accepted emeritus status. An innovative and remarkably productive researcher in a high-profile area in medical research, he was recipient of the laurels of his profession. A foreign member of the Royal Society and the Royal Society of Medicine in England, he was elected a member of the American Philosophical Society (1939), the National Academy of Sciences, and several similar societies in Denmark, Norway, and France, and he received honorary degrees from eight universities, including Cambridge, Michigan, Yale, and Chicago. A winner of the Kovalenko Medal of the National Academy of Sciences, the Distinguished Service Award of the American Cancer Society, the Lasker Award, the National Medal of Science, the Paul Ehrlich-Ludwig Darmstädter Award, and the United Nations Prize for Cancer Research, his career was capped with receipt of the Nobel Prize in 1966, shared equally with cancer researcher Charles B. Huggins of the University of Chicago, whose research centered on the relationship between hormones and prostate cancer.
Rous had three daughters with his wife, Marion Eckford DeKay, one of whom, Marion, married the Nobel laureate Alan Hodgkin. Rous died on February 16, 1970.